Howard Boat Photograph mss., 1980-1989 LMC 2276
Lilly Library
Howard Boat Photograph mss.
1980-1989
Lilly Library
LMC 2276
2 Boxes 2 standard
The Howard Boat Photograph Collection consists of copies made in the 1980's of photographs of river boats built by the Howard Shipyard & Dock Company at Jeffersonville, Indiana, between the 1860's and the 1930's.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
The Howard Shipyard and Dock Company is said to be the oldest continuous, at one time the largest, and in the post-Civil War period, the most famous shipyard of its kind on Western American rivers.
The shipyard was founded by James Howard, who was born in Oldham, England, on September 1, 1814, and brought to Cincinnati, Ohio, by his parents in 1820. After serving an apprenticeship to William Hartshorn, steamboat builder of Cincinnati, Howard established his own yards at Jeffersonville, Indiana, in 1834. In 1836 he moved his yards to Madison, Indiana, were he remained until 1844. The depression of 1844 induced him to spend the years 1844-1845 as an engineer and ship carpenter on the Ohio and Mississippi rivers. In 1846 he returned to the construction of steamboats locating his yards at Shippingsport, Kentucky. Soon he moved to Louisville, and from there in 1849 back to Jeffersonville, which became his permanent location. At this time he took his brother Daniel Howard in the firm. In 1865 his younger brother, John C. Howard, and his son, Edmonds John Howard, became his partners under the firm name, James Howard and Company. After the drowning of James Howard in 1876, his son and brother continued the business until the retirement of John C. Howard in 1888 left Edmonds John Howard in control. Under his presidency the business was expanded to include shipyards and marine ways at Cincinnati, Ohio, Madison and Jeffersonville, Indiana, Mound City, Illinois, and Paducah, Kentucky.
In January 1919 Clyde Howard and James E. Howard succeeded their father in the shipbuilding business. James was vice-president and buyer and Clyde the secretary and treasurer. The chair of president remained vacant. Upon the retirement of Clyde, James became the principal owner and president of the company.
From 1925 to 1941, Mrs. Loretta M. Howard, (Mrs. James E. Howard), was secretary and treasurer of the firm.
In 1942, the US Navy bought the shipyard, which was renamed the Jeffersonville Boat & Machine Company, and tank landing ships (LSTs) and submarine chasers for World War II were built there.
For the history of the firm, lists of boats constructed by it, and biographies of members of the Howard family see Lewis C. Baird's Baird's History of Clark County, Indiana. (Indianapolis, Ind., 1909), pp. 330-353, 431-433, 464-466, 733; Stephen G. Savage, "James Howard of Jeffersonville, Master Builder of Steamboats," master of arts thesis, Department of History, Indiana University, October 1952; and Charles Preston Fishbaugh, "The Howard Shipyards of Jeffersonville, Indiana, An Economic History," doctoral dissertation, School of Business, Indiana University, 1967, which was published as From Paddle Wheels to Propellers, Indianapolis. Indiana Historical Society, 1970 (VM301 .H6 F53).
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by name of boat.
Scope and Content Note
The Howard Boat Photograph Collection consists of copies made in the 1980's of photographs of river boats built by the Howard Shipyard & Dock Company at Jeffersonville, Indiana, between the 1860's and the 1930's. The copies were made from photographs located at the Murphy Library, University of Wisconsin, La Crosse, Wisconsin.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 1981-1982
Related Materials
See the Howard Oral History mss. and Howard Ship Yards and Dock Company mss., also at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
Voyages and travels; Boatbuilding; Boatyards; Indiana; photography; Howard Ship Yards and Dock Company
- A. Baldwin, 1905 (Box 1)
- A. D. Allen, 1901 (Box 1)
- Alonzo C. Church, 1893 (Box 1)
- Alton, 1906 (Box 1)
- Andrew Christy, 1897 (Box 1)
- Arthur Hider, 1898 (Box 1)
- A. M. Halliday (bridge view), 1903 (Box 1)
- A. M. Halliday (men on deck), 1903 (Box 1)
- Belle Memphis, 1880 (Box 1)
- Belle of the Bends, 1898 (Box 1)
- Blanks Cornwall, 1887 (Box 1)
- Bluff City, 1896 (Box 1)
- Bowling Green, 1904 (Box 1)
- Cape Girardeau, 1923 (Box 1)
- Chalmette, 1915 (Box 1)
- Charles J. Miller, 1925 (Box 1)
- Chicot, 1925 (Box 1)
- City of Baton Rouge, 1881 (Box 1)
- City of Baton Rouge, 1916 (Box 1)
- City of Bayou Sara, 1884 (Box 1)
- City of Cairo, 1882 (Box 1)
- City of Florence, 1909 (Box 1)
- City of Greenville, 1879 (Box 1)
- City of Helena, 1871 (Box 1)
- City of Hickman, 1890 (Box 1)
- City of Little Rock, 1893 (Box 1)
- City of Louisville, 1894 (Box 1)
- City of Memphis, 1898 (Box 1)
- City of Monroe, 1887 (Box 1)
- City of Muskogee, 1908 (Box 1)
- City of Natchez, 1885 (Box 1)
- City of New Orleans, 1881 (Box 1)
- City of Paducah, 1891 (Box 1)
- City of Providence, 1880 (Box 1)
- City of Peoria, 1892 (Box 1)
- City of Saltillo, 1905 (Box 1)
- City of Savannah, 1889 (Box 1)
- City of Savannah, 1902 (Box 1)
- City of Sheffield, 1890 (Box 1)
- City of Vicksburg, 1881 (Box 1)
- City of Warsaw, 1895 (Box 1)
- Col. A. MacKenzie, 1900 (Box 1)
- Cop-R-Loy, 1929 (Box 1)
- Crystal City, 1887 (Box 1)
- Dan Barrett, undated (Box 1)
- Demopolis, 1920 (Box 1)
- Dolphin No. 3, 1897 (Box 1)
- Donora, 1924 (Box 1)
- Dora Cabler, 1877 (Box 1)
- Duffy, 1921 (Box 1)
- E. R. Andrews, 1894 (Box 1)
- E. T. Slider, 1900 (Box 1)
- Ed Myer (Meyer?), 1909 (Box 1)
- Edna, 1914 (Box 1)
- Electra, 1897 (Box 1)
- Eliza, 1896 (Box 1)
- Everett Lee, 1931 (Box 1)
- G. W. Hill, 1909 (Box 2)
- General Craighill, 1911 (Box 2)
- General Logan, 1918 (Box 2)
- George W. Miller, 1926 (Box 2)
- Georgia Lee, 1898 (Box 2)
- Greenwood, 1898 (Box 2)
- H. St. L. Coppee, 1904 (Box 2)
- H. W. Buttorff, 1896 (Box 2)
- Hallette, 1887 (Box 2)
- Hiwassee (towboat), 1908 (Box 2)
- Homer Smith, 1914 (Box 2)
- Huntsville, 1893 (Box 2)
- Indiana, 1900 (Box 2)
- J. B. Richardson, 1898 (Box 2)
- J. G. Parke, 1882 (Box 2)
- J. H. Menge, 1910 (Box 2)
- J. O. Cole, 1900 (Box 2)
- James Lee, 1898 (Box 2)
- John Quill, 1907 (Box 2)
- Jupiter, 1912 (Box 2)
- Kate Adams, 1898 (Box 2)
- Kentucky, 1904 (Box 2)
- Lady Lee, 1889 (Box 2)
- Loretta Howard (towboat), 1929 (Box 2)
- Loretta Howard, 1929 (Box 2)
- Major Anderson, 1861 (Box 2)
- Mammoth Cave, 1908 (Box 2)
- Matt F. Allen, 1887 (Box 2)
- Merrill, 1908 (Box 2)
- Morning Star, 1901 (Box 2)
- Nashville, 1910 (Box 2)
- Natchez, 1891 (Box 2)
- Nugent, 1904 (Box 2)
- Ora Lee, 1891 (Box 2)
- Paducah, 1916 (Box 2)
- Patricia Barrett, 1927 (Box 2)
- Paul Tulane, 1888 (Box 2)
- Peoria, 1914 (Box 2)
- Peters Lee, 1899 (Box 2)
- R. Dunbar, 1895 (Box 2)
- Rene Macready, 1875 (Box 2)
- Robt. E. Lee, 1876 (Box 2)
- Rowena Lee, 1890 (Box 2)
- Robert E. Lee, 1876 (Box 2)
- Royal, 1904 (Box 2)
- Sadie Lee, 1901 (Box 2)
- Saint Louis, 1912 (Box 2)
- Saturn, 1912 (Box 2)
- Scimitar II, 1905 (Box 2)
- Senator Cordill, 1902 (Box 2)
- Sequoyah, 1925 (Box 2)
- Sergeant Floyd, 1932 (Box 2)
- Standard, 1915 (Box 2)
- W. K. Phillips, 1892 (Box 2)
- White Oak, 1905 (Box 2)
- Wm. Edenborn, undated (Box 2)
- Not catalogued, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2)